this is episode one of the Quant pie
insights where we're trying to get on
professionals like yourself Octavia
where we can understand what it's like
actually working as a Quant within the
industry so obviously you've described
yourself here as you've worked in the
Consulting industry in Spain Germany and
the US mainly is a derivative Quant and
doing Market risk now you're in
methodology and you're doing all types
of models at for investment banking at
South Santander would you be able to put
a little bit of perspective over your
background and your career journey to
date sure if you're a start of the year
I am from Argentina I study economics in
Argentina a kind of Economics also but
more oriented math
um I grew experiencing this because I
was supposed to work like anyone
everyone that study economy that is you
know in stock market just like
evaluation or whatever and I had a trip
to China and when I was in Shanghai like
6 seven years ago I saw all that
technology all that innovation
I say myself okay the words go to that
direction you know machine learning
models I need to understand their roots
and the causes of everything
that's what maybe my main concern was
okay I I can't be just at the top I need
to understand the route and if I
understand the models maybe I understand
the whole the whole problem and get a
solution or maybe a partial solution but
it was my my first question was okay how
can I understand how this
Finance World works you know and was
that an experience in which country were
you to have that experience it was that
was in China it was in China yeah it was
in China
[Music]
um
2016. excellent during during your study
obviously finished just finished just
finished my studies I went there because
I was studying University a lot about
China China is a very interesting
country for any economist
um and I wanted to to visit China I went
to China and it was like mind-blowing
it's amazing for anyone that that could
go China is very different like than
Argentina of course but also than Europe
or maybe oxy and the side of the world
and it's so different that is so richful
it's an amazing experience because
everything different in the different
culture different religion different
movement different Bible in the city and
yeah we should learn about that and they
had maybe
their course is more maybe more more
biased up to the quantitative skills
than Europe or maybe than than Latin
America so they are more Quant skill and
of course that's why we had in the
industry a lot of Chinese Asian or
Indian people a lot because they are
really good at math they're really good
at programming and they're really good
focusing some that is very very useful
in the quantum world that it's with
focusing a problem and to get the
solution the problem
so that could be um yeah that could just
be background and the way the education
systems work in in different different
countries I can definitely speak to that
um the education system I've experienced
a little bit in England at top
universities at Imperial College London
um just doing a one-year Exchange
program while I was studying chemical
engineering and it was apples and
oranges compared to what I was learning
at the University of Queensland in
Australia so look um that's really
interesting so so you've come out of
your bachelor's degree and you've gone
and you've had this incredible
experience
um in China and you've seen a lot of
things you're asking a lot of questions
about I want to understand this this is
where my motivations come in what did
you do after that how did you follow
that Curiosity
Finance in Spain we have while I moved
to Spain in Spain there are two maybe
two big Master degrees into different
universities I had one of that that was
another very great experience because
it's very intensive and mathematic in
let's say in python or r or Java or C
plus plus in programming skills and
little bit of Finance to be honest in
this world you need to know
program to program math the finance part
is is important but let's say a five
percent in comparison to the to the
other skills I did a master and and
during the master I get to to a big four
and then from the big four I continue
working in the consultant of the
industry I have to know that I'm in in
the bank and so you were working as a
quantitative consultant for around one
of the big four
um institutions yeah yes yes I work as a
quan first I start in the in the audit
side that it was it was a very good
experience because
the weak Force has maybe two big lines
or assurance and consultants and
assurance
we need to audit all the river tips so
we need to do the pricing of all the
derivatives yeah and that's very
challenged because you need to really
match the result at the fourth five
decimal you know so during the skill is
very challenging because when someone
works in the college or let's say in the
early stage of your professional career
you kind of try to match a result but if
it's you know let's say one percent up
or down it's okay but when you are in
the tree each decimal is money so you
need to be really precisely and good in
the result that's let's say uh a
training is in this world to be really
accurate wow so um so as as part of that
Consulting who were your clients that
you were assistant build these Financial
models for evaluation models a lot a lot
of banks a lot of companies out of
insurance different kind of company for
smart remember pizza companies yeah
swaps wow it was really really amazing
they you know here in Spain you have a
very big a big pizza restaurant that I
always eat and eat in the street that it
was my clients because they have some
swaps and they need to to cover the
pricing it was amazing all kind of fun
yes it deepest the market you have more
clients every kind of corporate
Insurance Banks whatever Financial
companies also you are obviously had
some really good experience over these
couple of years what do you think so in
terms of being able to be at a
consulting firm as a Quant and being
able to see all these different
businesses and price all these different
products what type of skills do you
think that you picked up along the way
maybe during your masters of
mathematical finance that actually
assisted you in doing the on job
requirements everything that your boss
required you to do what really helped
you I think that that question has two
two different species that is if you see
use the Bible your career life in the
beginning and then your medium career
life at the beginning of One Life you
need to be good programming because
of course you will need mathematics but
you will need you will need to be good
at programming because when you are a
junior or maybe when you are an intern
you need to get some stuff automated or
you need to program some codes so that's
what you need at the first instance then
of course you will need mathematics
depending on each of the portfolio if
you are more
focus on Trading a trade inside
in the trading book you need to know a
lot of calculus
that's that's maybe the the most
difficult is also the same is the root
of how we model the you know the path on
the stocks or any uh underline so when
you need to understand at least Calculus
if you're not going to model you need to
understand or to be able to read a paper
to understand how ability volatility
surface is calibrated you need to
understand the models but about it is
maybe I remember when I was starting in
the news today was like very
confuse or or maybe upset because I
didn't knew anything and maybe the first
thing that you you think that you should
know about every anything and this world
is very difficult it's very complex you
need to understand the things in a very
deep way and there is a time for that
you know you need to be evolving okay so
you're actually recommending that um if
people start off as more generalists and
they focus as a young professional on
the actual coding implementation and
being able to do things and impress your
boss that is going to mean a lot more
and then you're going to get technical
and involved into deep projects as you
develop through your career is that by
far by far um because do we have a
senior yes and that senior we know more
mathematics than you or maybe we'll know
more about how to apply Than Mathematics
okay
the background here all our like
Engineers or mathematics or physics and
they they all know mathematics but maybe
they do not know how to apply that
mathematics
or to model the mathematics so your
senior will be able to say okay for this
model we need to do a markup chain for
this this morning we need to know
whatever you know that's that's practice
that that's to understand the products
and which mathematical methods you we
need to use for each problem
yeah yeah oh that's fantastic and um so
in terms of like these critical Concepts
and methodologies that you've actually
used in your role especially during
those um times that you're related to
Market risk and derivative pricing
during your Consulting time
um what was the most useful
um skill set that you could you could
apply
that that's that that's a very good
question
um
while you will need a stochastic
calculus by by far yes sorry so so and
this is something that you did that
you're capturing your Masters yeah but
um did you find at least for me when I
was going through my Master's
mathematical Finance half the time
um you get intro more interested in the
subject when you're actually applying it
on the job then at the time when you are
actually learning the thing during your
master's program so I I I found that in
my own work that whenever then I'm
delving into a new problem and I have
exposure to the topic so then I know
which resources that I can go to or what
type of math that I need but then I'm
going back to my old textbooks to to
revisit the models and learn more is
that a similar approach to what you're
exactly it's exactly the same approach
we I remember that we had in the in the
office we had all the main books the
main Bibles of this world you know
Willie mod whole uh all the Bible script
same models or whatever and we are
always looking at this model because it
is really difficult to remember of the
model let's say one week ago one week
ago here at the bank
front office came with a kind of project
to simulate let's say the collateral of
a model that it should follow
a given path and then have a jump
distribution and of course I forget how
to do that so I went back to the to the
box and I started reading all the
mathematics methodology and continuous
side how to model whatever jump models
yes yeah more so
is I mean maybe I think it's almost
impossible to remember all the all the
models but to cut the books
if you understand the framework yes
you could go to the bibliography and do
this of course no that's that's
excellent and I think really good advice
for Ram listeners to to follow
um especially when they're starting off
in their career so as as your roles
obviously evolved and you've
transitioned throughout your career now
you're very now you're covering various
models um at your new job at Santander
you're looking at all these different
models and methodologies
um across different investing Investment
Banking applications how how different
is that now where you're taking a high
level approach and I assume maybe you
have a team of analysts that you're
helping delegate work to how does the
quantitative role change now and do you
still get to get dug into the tools
hey a lot because maybe when I change
from consultancy to to the bank industry
I used to change to credit and credit is
verification on the market Incredibles
more you use more econometric tools
statistical tools that is quite
different from Market risk it's a
different kind of mathematics it's more
statistics
and also because in my bank we are
really strong in the credit side they
are just starting for example trying to
understand the risk of a digitalization
that's very complex so in that world or
CVA right xva we're also trying to
understand about the risk but is the
same you have a Tools in your Quant
toolbox okay enough simulation I know
how to do a medical simulation okay so
maybe I could use Monte Carlo to check
we must check I simulate you know the
expected default into my portfolio so
when you have a toolbox it's amazing you
know for me the best thing that you can
do in this work to
beam in love with the problems and to
get Solutions because we are every day
will be different to be honest and you
need to be the the kind of person love
to solve problems yes and I think I
think we were just speaking about that
before um and just about some of the
challenges but also then opportunities
that you have working at such a big bank
and having to navigate some of those
problems you said one of the significant
problems is even just when you get
dedicated a new model that has to be
developed on your desk that's actually a
new line of the business that needs to
be formed and therefore you're having to
interact with front office you're having
to interact with back office how is that
is that one of the more challenging
aspects of your role that's the main
challenge of the role by by far you know
the easiest way of my job is to learn
more to create a model this is the
easiest way
because when you create a model do you
do
you spend some time thinking about how
to grow the model how this will behave
Etc but then you have your user let's
say okay I don't like this kind of more
because this value will not fit like a
well for me and then you have different
stakeholders and you you need to connect
each stakeholder with your model and to
get results and each stakeholder in a
big organization should be should agree
with the results of your model
and your models create a discipline
because
let's say we're in a bank okay the bank
the main use of a bank is to let's say
lend money to develop new business lines
with that premise we need to be just
behind of them trying to give a
discipline and trying to provide
accurate models to accredit measured
risk I could measure how much line
consumption we will have how much
Capital will we need to have
improvisions or whatever so our model
size is really critical and it's also
it's also obligatory because of
Regulation so obviously you know the the
but it is as you've kind of indicated it
sounds like this is more of a secondary
let's tick the box to The Regulators
um why we have these risk models in
place okay that's ready yeah that's
right that's right that well so I think
that of course always is a regulatory
side but is a different step first of
all you developer model and then you fit
your model when the regulatory with the
with the guidelines of the regulatory
framework and whatever but in the first
instance you try to be creative okay
let's we have this problem let's be
creative with the front office okay we
could provide this and this models and
then once we have this okay let's go
with the regulator the show our model we
need to be really precise in our model
and to be also responsible with our risk
because
how we managed and we see how the people
will be as confident with us you know if
they trust with us because we got very
good models and because we are really
good and I believe that we're really
good estimating risk you know but that's
kind of incentives we have front office
that try to make increased Vision Line
and we are risk we are trying to measure
accurately at the front office okay up
to here you can do business then it's
our side you know but philosophically
the model is the pillar
yeah well that makes a lot of sense so
in terms so that's the that's the
challenges aspect
um I guess from your perspective what
opportunities do those kind of
challenges present for yeah uh people
who want to start and they want to
understand those relationships and they
want to get going in their career and
potentially make it to where you have at
a bank like that how can they navigate
those challenges what are the
opportunities for new people coming into
this established banking system where
the practices are like that for the
quantware it's a secondary consideration
well they need to understand the Quant
part is just the beginning of this you
know this world we we of course we we
more focus on how we create the model
but we will also need to understand how
our bank works
or the same when you are consultant we
reconcile that your client is your is
your bank or your financial company and
you agree with them more but you need to
understand how that model fits to your
clients no it's like when you go with
your card today
mechanic you will need to be very clear
with him or how do you want to to be to
to fix your car because if not
he might charge you overcharge you for
your services you might get a pair of uh
that's great that's correct and our
industry is really really in a
inflection in an inflection point
because
all this increasing AI Technologies
I don't know how this
will continue how this will evolve in
the time but it's really it's really
powerful do you think that that's a
challenge and um for a big bank to adopt
new AI tools
um for example Robo advising for clients
and things like that is it is it a large
challenge but is it also an opportunity
where you're at that's correct because
we have well we always have to cite the
Regulatory and economic side in the
regulatory side
the regulator up to now is not very
comfortable in the machine learning
models because it's a black box
and you need to understand what is is
doing your model you know for example
let's say I really really easy
methodology there is a logistic
regression
to predict one or zero so that's really
used and this is really powerful
but it was invented to be done with a
pencil you know like we are still using
the same model but it's really powerful
so the regulator on the standard model
we're trying to predict bad or good
instead of default or no default and
that's correct but in a machine learning
model
is a kind of backup boxing which you
give a parameters they say how many
parameters will be in your model because
of the each I know grid search or
whatever and then how that will give to
you
a final decision
and that's a black box and that's let's
say up to now is not uh the the
preferable solution for the regulator
but maybe in the future yes maybe or
maybe also our
is to try to understand really how these
mods work and I think a lot of people
use machine learning but they don't
understand how they work
in your section there with credit risk
and um uh so actual valuation of credit
party risk just understanding that when
you are modified when you are modeling
it from a portfolio approach just having
um a non-transient matrix which has been
traditionally done and causes a lot of
issues I guess novel techniques of the
likes of machine learning where you're
not just doing Simple regression over a
period of time to get your coefficients
to this transition Matrix
um to actually be coming up with a model
that's maybe transient and has different
regime switching I I assume that there
are some great modeling techniques what
what opportunities do you see there
specifically in your field within that
technical detail of modeling credit
party
um counter risk I I I see a lot in the
let's say in
in the high default portfolio let's say
for example credit and credit credit
cards debt or whatever it's whatever
folder has a lot of homogeneity of a lot
of adapter and very homogeneous whatever
we could use machine learning also in
the front office one side
there's a lot of potential in in using
machine learning to stock prediction or
whatever this was that I know in your
channel you promote a lot of this
there's a big and big opportunity there
in the front of in the market in the
market side because that is economic
side you know is like yeah business
making and yes that's correct this is
very different
[Music]
um
but that's one one let's say one
Challenge and the second one that is one
that I'm working currently is the ESG oh
yes the ESG risk a I am working actually
creating a model uh all the banks are
are working this line uh to be more
responsible
um and the climate change issues the
environmental the social issues are
really difficult to model
you need to be very creative that's
something that they mentioned but in
this job do we need to be really
creative you need to read a lot not only
mathematics mathematics only sorry not a
only mathematical also you need to
understand the problem
in letting climate change risk you need
to understand what you are modeling and
that's nothing among mathematical or
about what I learned in the master that
is a place for derivative or whatever is
okay I have this issue
how would they Bend or sorry we have a
lot of Channel vendors in the industry
like SMP msci whatever you've got a lot
of pH well all the all these that are
let's say are the same you have a lot of
vendor that provides to you data but
what do you do with that data about
climate change how do you model how do
you create let's say ratings if you need
to
to increase your business with a client
that is not comply that not that does
not comply with the ESG requirement or
with the taxonomies of the ratchet what
happened how do you create a model it's
very difficult and you need to really be
creative
uh I guess this is the kind of thing
that um yeah I mean it's just like with
counterparty risk when when when you're
assigning based on your qualitative
factors
um you know your counterparty risk with
certain individuals
much the same as future Moody would do
um then you can really upset your
counterparty and you can end up um you
know by closing them
um you know a grievance in in kind of
that threshold for the variation margin
and I assume that that will be the new
topic of conversation with this ESG
stuff if you're if you're having to
assign a factor to each investment
project to each
um you know collaborator potential
business partner if you're having to cut
you know come up with an ESG metric and
decisions are being made oh well we
can't invest with you because you're
you're polluting you know too much CO2
with your projects I guess that's going
to be the new trade-off
for sure that's the typical admission
and Mission problem which do we admit
outside or not you know in the bank you
have that's maybe one of the main
important uh roles in in the risk side
that is okay do we admit this client or
not right yeah depending on we have a
lot of factors we of course we study
where the companies and Etc but the ESG
is really really important and we are in
that kind in that in that case we have
the commonly a friend of the name beta
problem in which we don't have enough
data that is something that we also need
to understand sequence and although we
will have data not always we are dealing
with stocks or with optional liquids and
cabata when we don't have data which
kind of mathematics do we use we use
non-parametric mathematics with
parametric and you know what what is the
best approach to do
um
in ESG not all the companies make
disclosure of the information maybe they
don't have enough incentives maybe yes
but or maybe done yet so that's the the
data problem is very important in our in
our job and we need to understand which
methods should we use that is much more
accurate to to estimate this risk yes
and say and and that's where I guess
just looping back to what you said
before about having the right framework
and learning the right Frameworks to
approach problems with him and just
having a problem-solving approach so for
example in my uh engineering degree you
know we learned how to do bottom-up
um you know like the elong musk approach
first principles so that's kind of how
ESG would be handled from a chemical
engineer they'd start drawing a bunch of
boxes around processes and say what's
going in what's going out doing you know
carbon dioxide balances and all that so
I guess I guess those Frameworks and
skills are really important to pick up
along the way and I guess moving into
that what what advice do you have for
aspiring quantitative analysts what
skills and qualifications do you believe
are essential for someone aiming to
become a successful derivative quads
Market risk consultant yeah a
quantitative analyst I know quite good
courses in one by in the quantify
of course your courses are by far very
recommended but nowadays we have a lot
of offer that's that's really great
let's say moocs we have some Bibles and
some Bibles that maybe they are they're
really different tools so you said John
C John C how you referenced before yes
of course a will mod I don't remember
now the name that you I saw a video of
you I come in my how the two little
books that are blue about the category
and discrete and continuous model tennis
model I forget this is the the author
um
depending in exp you have also like some
Bibles you know you know to have some
Bible yeah to to refer in each case
um and I guess I guess from those
resources what what are you really
picking up is the is is it is it the
framework you know because as we said
you know we can use them as references
for specific problems but the tool sets
that you take away like being able to
understand uh probability and statistics
and that things aren't just a point
value value at risk if there's a
probability there or understanding Monte
Carlo simulation yeah yeah for sure for
me how I work is
really a toolbox in which I know which
kind of eye color I need to apply
uh if I need to to estimate different
states for example yeah I need to use a
Markov chain in this scenario whatever
uh if I need to to do some regression
which kind of linear nonlinear
regression I have in my toolbox in my
head and in which case each one could
fit or not
if we talk about calculus of course you
will need to know multiply the calculus
but
let's let's I think we need to
understand very good the basics algebra
calculus of one variables calculus or
two or more variables
sorry two words I'm multiplying calculus
and then I give accurate as you know
these three algebra calculus and
probability and statistics sorry
you're good yeah you're going to be good
for your career that's that's the
pillars that's the pillar and it's not
too much if you study let's say calculus
the famous book about calculus that's
called calculus yeah if you study from
from also a algebra there is a very good
from I think most a
well done I think it's a really good
book about a algebra in probability
versica that is an MIT professional of
the probability is really good or for
Ross
if you know that books you are really
good then of course then of course you
will understand you will need to
understand how to do a Monte Carlo
simulation in in finance but you need
these Basics the same in Python
you will need python but there is some
level in which the banks has
another type of programming language
like C plus plus or C sharp or C why
because maybe at the past maybe of
course they are better
but maybe also because sometimes you
program in the language as your boss
knows and not in the language that you
should you know that the industry goes
not only amongst us python why maybe
because they both at least in that's in
that team no R and prefer R so you will
need to adapt to r or to SAS
you know or to C plus plus or to Koval
do but if you know how to program and if
you know the logical of how to program
you're good you're good to continue you
have to do uh let's say some currencies
and to be updated with the last news and
then very good oh that's really that's
really helpful I guess for those books
um that you've recommended there we
might put links down in the description
I'll get you to see three different ones
that you think are really valuable so
our listeners can help sure
um and I guess yeah the other side of
this is career progression how so you
know as someone who has been able to you
know transition from a market you know
Market
um risk consulting position where you're
looking at derivative valuation and
portfolio evaluations for front office
to then transitioning now to credit risk
and you know being being more in a
management type position with with a
team can you share some insights on that
transition
um and kind of a tools you know the
things that helped you adjust to the new
role and and just some advice for people
who are young Professionals in their
careers who want to progress and move
forward their career in quantitative
Finance yes so my first recommendation
is again love to solve problems you will
need to be the kind of personal lab to
solve problems because when you move
from Market to credit of course you
don't know any nothing about credit that
that's that's that's the reality I when
I moved to this position was okay I'm
new I need to study my free time
credit
but as I have in my toolbox probability
algera calculus it was easier for me
also of course I did a master whatever
but I had in my header a toolbox so okay
I had these tools I just need to refresh
these tools so if you move to Market or
or to credit if you know the base
then you will need to be the kind of
person that
that want to to
to make a lot of Errors you know I I
mean in this job the error is on my side
because when I have like in in my
position actually actually I am
every day trying to solve problems that
doesn't have a solution
okay when I was an audit I I was trying
to price an option with barrier or
whatever but you know that if you just
do a simulation and if you really are
good Parliament if when you parameter is
very good the barriers or let's say if
the strikes instead of being a shot of
fixed strike you have a sticky Sprites a
strike or you have on the average of
strikes or whatever the more complex but
you know what you need to convert to a
market value because you are using
Market inputs volatility the dividend
whatever
there are some problems in the industry
that doesn't have a solution so when you
need to be creative and you need to know
that you are going to make a lot of
Errors errors I mean that will not maybe
will not be good for your boss but it's
okay I will give you tomorrow another
model and that's how you invent new
things yeah that's I think sorry yeah
being able to take on those new projects
and being able to progress them and take
ownership over them is that being being
someone who's willing to take risk and
learn
um if you're saying that that's going to
get you in your career yeah for life of
a career yeah okay willing to take a
risk and to
you know we we need to also enjoy this
job and we are like inventors we are
always trying to learn something new and
do you need to try different
Alternatives some some ones are going to
be really good some are not maybe at the
average you will be okay
but of course yeah yeah that I think
that's that's for me that's we always
worked and it was really proactive I was
always trying to think about different
solutions but new solution and the
there's kind of trade-off here that is
for me really
a important later is to you know in this
life we are always going to pass so we
need to do things that that will keep
forever that's my mentality I work with
a model that I would
be at the bank once that I will not be
here anymore so we need to do to be very
professional we need to create more that
are really well constructed we really
Define really good boundaries the
mathematics is well documented
if we create a good model the model will
be there forever and that's this truly
true unless something happens to change
but at least for 10 years the money will
be in the bank so if we are going to
creating more and if we really are
professional our job will be
in that play for a lot of time another
job in this country in definitely not if
you are maybe in the markets any day
every day the the things change so it's
what you raise and you start again in
the day but in this kind of of job you
are creating new things that could be
a lot of fun in the in your company yeah
oh that's really satisfying
um just just to understand that in the
banking world you know I guess when most
people hear the word Quant they're
thinking they want to work in
quantitative trading they want to be
doing derivatives valuations Market
making they want to be on you know on
the front desk as a quantitative analyst
but that's a really interesting
perspective that if you are in the model
model development team and you are in a
bank
you are creating something that's going
to kind of last and be used for the
entire duration of that business
um duration and not only that it's going
to be something that's really durable
we're really robust and like you're
saying the model validation piece that
goes around it the model validation that
goes around it and the documentation is
incredibly or sounds like it's
incredibly
um rigorous so that's yeah yeah that's
correct we're in the in the Quan this
one industry we have a lot of different
roles it could be validation with audit
or audit it could be also methodology
team could be a quants it could be
Trader that's a lot of Traders nowadays
that are not really quants yeah that are
really good and Mathematics and maybe
they were quantity they pass and now
they go to and they pass to be a Trader
so we are in every place the good thing
is that is that if you know mathematics
if you know this toolbox these Basics
you could work in any place
that's really good advice and um I guess
yeah closing closing thoughts and
recommendations I guess just hearing
more from your personal experience is
there is there a particular
accomplishment or a project
um from your career that you're
particularly proud of and would like to
share with the audience something that
you're kind of encapsulating those
that's lasted time that will be at the
bank for as long as possible or maybe
it's a moment from your Consulting
career of course of course I mean
when you create models let's say rating
if I I work in a bank that they credit a
side of the bank is very good the credit
book is really really big and all the
credit side is based on three parameters
I said the probability of default the
rate that is and the rate that is mapped
to that probability of defaults the lgd
and EAD but the ratings of your clients
are really the pillar of your bank
if you are good creating that ratings if
you create a model for that ratings that
is really fits well all the banks are
going to apply assign a product to
default for the client that was created
by you now so I will repeat this
all the clients in the bank has a
probability of defaults if you create a
model
you will be in each transaction of the
bank
because because are you saying the banks
right now are looking outside for these
rating models are they not developing
them in in-house no they depending on
which portfolio and depending of if you
have internal or external defaults you
could use your own PD modelers or
external PV models and also depending on
the size of your bank that's that's
really no a and also because it's more
complexity because if you are in a
standard approach or internal model
based approach you will create your own
model or maybe you will use for Capital
another kind of money okay but that's
very complex but
in in my job I create things that my my
spirit is in
any part of the bank nobody knows but I
know and that's really good because the
people for the people is has an input
yes of course and that value is my it's
it's my soul that's that's really great
I remember I had just an anecdote when I
was in consultant we we program
calculators okay to to buy to price
derivatives and we sell that to
different banks and when we did
simulations you know we have
um the the root is in English the auto
simulation is should be a fixed value if
you need to be the audit right if you
are selling audit tools should be you
should be able to
use a fix a route to kind of have
traceability of that simulation okay
so we use our names in the in the root
that nobody knows but my name is in a
lot of creators
instead of being distributed
within the bank you're talking about now
my my neighbor not my name is just in
like Octavio it's my name with different
kind of
when I worked in the consultant industry
we sell calculator for 12. to some
client oh so you're you're proud of your
calculators that are now sitting with
this wide diverse range of clients
and nobody knows that's that's really
good that's really good when you create
models the model will last in with your
claim for a lot of time as long as
you're building stuff it's good value
well documented as you said often that's
really really important recommendations
recommendation is a key part
a in our job because when we program we
need to be really good documenting our
our code our script if if not the the
guy that is going to be behind of you
will not understand that so you will
need really be good documenting this and
also in your model need to be really
documented your your assumptions every
anything
I think that's really important and
that's something that I learned um yeah
in the first couple of years I was kind
of like oh well I'll keep everything I'm
working on siled in this box you know
you know I I want to show my boss how
good I am compared to the analyst next
to me but that's really the wrong
approach I've I've found throughout my
career it's so much better to focus on
actually doing yourself out of the job
you want to be so good at your job and
document all the processes so well list
all the assumptions out that you could
be replaced tomorrow
and then that you know people kind of
have fear of that documentation you do
yourself out of the job well it actually
um gives your you more free time to work
on more interesting problems and then
potentially advancing your career
that's correct yeah yeah also the the
capability to reuse your code so your
reuse part of your models let's say
again the example of a markup change we
use the microchips in a lot of different
models if we create this in Python the
objects right if you are we are object
oriented programming okay if we create
an object now do this and it's well
documented then the next guide I need to
use this tool we'll just use my my code
so if you are very you have a repository
that is really clean there is really
well documented then we need to do the
things just one time
saves a lot of resources doesn't it
that's the toolbox instead of being my
head now is a repository in Python in in
any in GitHub and whatever now nowadays
you have a lot of different place but in
any repository you will have all the
codes and that teamwork literally
teamwork and then as is Orange
um object-oriented programming you need
just to create an ad object that would
inherit that object but you know it is
it's already done so that that's really
fantastic very fantastic
and we're always improving our last
version that's really good yeah and then
that does sound really good so yeah
using Code repositories and making sure
that you're
um making all your comments and listing
all your assumptions
um so I guess to conclude what what
actionable advice
um or final thoughts do you have for the
young professionals students who are
listening to us today um to actually
follow a similar career path as you you
know we spoke about before that you kind
of started From economics and you you
know you're you weren't in Quant Finance
but you were motivated having had that
experience in China and you went back
and you studied so you're not starting
as someone who started off as an IV
League school and you know you you you
you went down the process and you got
picked up by a Quant firm straight away
you're someone who's been starting down
the path potentially like a lot of our
listeners So to that person to yourself
when you first started out what what
advice would you give to them to kind of
to follow a similar career path I will
say that it will be very very hard
that's true if you came from an economic
career it will be really hard never give
up that's really true never give up it
will really hard because in economics we
don't have the enough background but
it's really worth it it's really worth
it uh
try always to learn the new approaches
so I always will think out of the box
and try to understand the whole picture
where you stand
okay because
we're always going to evolve so we are
now a quants of this portfolio but maybe
tomorrow for another portfolio and
tomorrow maybe the CEO of the bank I
don't know but we need to understand the
whole picture
the whole picture even the whole picture
let's say interest rate models we
understand the whole framework of
interesting model and then we calibrate
the Curve you know and then we have
either project I know anyone anyone
knows that is some two or three years
ago our interest our risk-free rates
change
from in advance in terms rate to Inner
real interest rate let's say that
how they fix change okay that was really
really important change in the in the
industry but if we don't understand the
whole picture we'll never be able to
understand how this will impact in
different kind of day of the bank
so for me that's the the the main advice
is never give up it will really hard but
it's really worth it and once you have
this Toolbox will it will be really fun
you're always enjoying your job because
you are always like playing games and
this is really true
for me it's just sometimes it has to
play playing games I am with my music
programming thinking about the problem
and that's my day-to-day job and that's
pretty good yeah oh that's fantastic
well thank you so much for coming on
Octavio it was really great to have you
thank you thank you too nice to meet you
[Music]
thank you